Guide to the Mabel Dodge Luhan Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mabel Dodge Luhan collection
1885-1984
YCAL MSS 197
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.97
(7 boxes) + 2 art
The Luhan collection consists of letters, manuscripts, photographs, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Mabel Dodge Luhan. There is correspondence with psychoanalyst Abraham Arden Brill, Dr. Eric P. Hauser, and friend and assistant Walter Willard Johnson. There are smaller groups of letters to Charlotte Becker and Robert Edmond Jones, as well as incoming letters from John Reed. Writings include drafts of several manuscripts: typescript carbon drafts of "Hildegaard" and Una and Robin; a holograph draft of Edge of Taos Desert; a holograph and typescript draft of the unpublished "Family Affairs"; holograph and typescript drafts of Movers and Shakers; the original holograph manuscript of the unpublished novel "Water of Life"; and the first draft of Winter in Taos. There are early photographs of Luhan, photographs of friends, including Dorothy Brett and Robinson and Una Jeffers, and photographs of Luhan's homes in Taos, New Mexico, and Florence. Personal papers include the painting of Luhan by Mary Foote.
Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1879-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mabel Dodge Luhan Collection was acquired through various gifts and purchases dating from 1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
Material related to Mabel Dodge Luhan that was donated to the library by Mabel Dodge Luhan is located in the Mabel Dodge Luhan Papers (YCAL MSS 196).
MABEL DODGE LUHAN (1879-1962)
Mabel Dodge Luhan was a major cultural figure in the United States in the first half of the 20th century. She is best known as a patron of the arts and writer, author of a multi-volume autobiographical work and books on D. H. Lawrence, Taos, and Taos area artists. There is considerable scholarship on Luhan, and there are book-length biographical studies by Emily Hahn (1977), Winifred Frazer (1984), and Lois Palken Rudnick (1984). Summary information is available in the standard print and online biographical resources.
The following chronology provides dates for key events and publications:
1879 February 26, born in Buffalo, New York to Charles F. Ganson and Sara McKay Cook
?-95 attends St. Margaret's Episcopal School for Girls in Buffalo
1895-96 attends Miss Graham's School in New York City
1896-97 attends Chevy Chase School in Washington, D.C.
1900 marries Karl Kellog Evans
1902 birth of son John Ganson Evans; death of Charles F. Ganson
1903 death of Karl Kellog Evans
1904 travels to Paris; meets and marries Edwin Sherrill Dodge
1905 moves to Villa Curonia, Florence
1911 meets Gertrude and Leo Stein
1912 Gertrude Stein writes "The Portrait of Mabel Dodge at the Villa Curonia"; moves to New York City
1913-14 presides over salon; contributes to the International Exhibition of Modern Art and Paterson Strike Pageant
1915 contributes to the formation of the Elizabeth Duncan School in Croton-on-Hudson, New York
1916 undergoes therapy with Smith Ely Jelliffe, Emma Curtis Hopkins, and Abraham Arden Brill; formally divorced from Edwin Sherrill Dodge
1917 writes for newspapers; marries Maurice Sterne; moves to Taos, New Mexico
1918 meets Antonio Lujan; acquires property ("Los Gallos") in Taos
1922 contributes to campaign against Bursum Bill; formally divorced from Maurice Sterne; hosts D. H. and Frieda Lawrence
1923 marries Antonio Lujan
1924 publication of "Ballad of a Bad Girl"
1925-26 corresponds with members of Georges Ivanovitch Gurdjieff's circle and invites Gurdjieff to relocate to New Mexico
1926 hosts Paul Strand and Rebecca Salsbury James
1929 hosts Georgia O'Keeffe, John Marin, and Ansel Adams; performance of Witter Bynner's Cake by Santa Fe Players
1932 publication of Lorenzo in Taos
1933 publication of Background, first volume of Intimate Memories
1935 publication of European Experiences, second volume of Intimate Memories
1935 publication of Winter in Taos
1936 publication of Movers and Shakers, third volume of Intimate Memories; donates property ("La Posta") to Taos for new county hospital
1937 publication of Edge of Taos Desert, forth volume of Intimate Memories
1947 publication of Taos and its Artists
1951 donates papers to Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University
1962 August 13, dies in Taos, New Mexico
Scope and Contents
The Mabel Dodge Luhan Collection consists of letters, manuscripts, photographs, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Mabel Dodge Luhan. The collection spans the years 1885-1984.
The collection is housed in seven boxes and organized into seven series according to provenance: Charlotte Becker Purchase, Edmund R. Brill Gifts, Margaret Heyman Gift, Walter Willard Johnson Purchase, Richard B. Streeper Gift, Carl Van Vechten Gifts, and Material from Other Sources. Boxes 6-7 contain Oversize and Restricted Fragile material respectively.
Series I, Charlotte Becker Purchase, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, Photographs, and Other Papers.
This series consists of various material acquired by Becker, a native of Buffalo, dating from late 19th century photographs of Luhan to 1940. The Correspondence consists entirely of incoming letters and postcards from Luhan and Walter Willard ("Spud") Johnson. There are numerous postcards from Luhan, many from abroad, and a few letters, dating from the 1930s, discussing family, friends, and book projects. In addition, there are a few articles, at least one of which ("Women Who Seek...") does not appear to duplicate material in the Mabel Dodge Luhan Papers (YCAL MSS 196).
Series II, Edmund R. Brill Gifts, is also organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, Photographs, and Other Papers.
The bulk of the Correspondence in Series II consists of letters between Luhan and Dr. Abraham Arden Brill, one of the first practicing psychoanalysts in the United States. Luhan started analysis with Brill in 1916, and the two maintained a long working relationship and friendship. Most letters date from the 1930s, during which time Luhan put out Lorenzo in Taos and Intimate Memories. Luhan's letters to Brill touch on her work and experience, psychoanalytic and Freudian concepts, and friends. Brill's letters (carbons) provide interpretations of feelings and actions described in Luhan's letters, impressions of Luhan's writings, including an account of her analysis ("Psychoanalysis with Dr. Brill"), and considerable encouragement.
The Correspondence includes several postcards from John Reed to Luhan, dating from 1917, and several letters from others regarding D. H. Lawrence, most dating from the 1930s, including third-party letters to and from D. H. and Frieda Lawrence.
Other noteworthy items in this series include a watercolor painting by Luhan in Other Papers and corrected, typescript carbon drafts of the manuscripts "Hildegarde" and "Una and Robin" in Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan.
Series III, Margaret Heyman Gift, consists of 14 photogaphs arranged alphabetically by the name of the person(s) portrayed. There are photographs of Mabel and Tony Luhan, Dorothy Brett, Robinson and Una Jeffers, Mrs. Abraham Arden Brill, and Mrs. Marcus Babcock Heyman.
Series IV, Walter Willard Johnson Purchase, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, and Other Papers.
The bulk of the correspondence, six of seven total folders, consists of original letters from Luhan to Walter Willard or "Spud" Johnson. Johnson co-edited a small publication in Santa Fe entitled Laughing Horse, to which Luhan contributed articles in the 1920s. He also worked as a secretary to Luhan. Luhan's letters to Johnson date from 1927-58, include many brief postcards, telegrams, and notes, and cover work and personal matters. A few letters are addressed both to Johnson and Witter "Hal" Bynner. Letters between Luhan and others are arranged in choronological order in the folder "Other Correspondence."
Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, housed in boxes 2-5, includes several pieces of writing that cannot be found in the Luhan Papers (YCAL MSS 196). There are incomplete drafts of several longer writings: a holograph draft of Edge of Taos Desert; a manuscript, in holograph and typescript, of the unpublished "Family Affairs"; holograph and typescript drafts of Movers & Shakers; the original holograph manuscript of the unpublished novel "Water of Life"; and the first draft, corrected, of Winter in Taos. In addition, there are manuscripts of several shorter articles and narratives. Presumably these manuscripts came into Johnson's possession when he worked for Luhan.
Series V, Richard B. Streeper Gift, consists of four folders of correspondence between Luhan and Dr. Eric P. Hausner. Letters date from 1946-58 and deal largely with matters of physical health and family, though in one letter, dated "Nov. 12, 1954," Luhan mentions her essay "Doctors: Fifty Years of Experience."
Series VI, Carl Van Vechten Gifts, is organized into two subseries: Photographs and Other Papers.
The Writings subseries includes four pieces of writing by Luhan and a typescript copy of Gertrude Stein's famous essay, "Portrait of Mabel Dodge at the Villa Curonia." There are two printed articles, "Georgia O'Keeffe in Taos" and "The Santos of New Mexico," which cannot be found in the Luhan Papers (YCAL MSS 196), and a bound typescript draft of Chapter V of European Experiences entitled "Portrait of the Villa Curonia." This bound draft includes photographs of Luhan and the Villa Curonia by painter Jacques-Emile Blanche.
Photographs contains photographs of Mabel and Tony Luhan, the Villa Curonia, and "Los Gallos," Luhan's property in Taos.
Series VII, Material from Other Sources, consists of single items from other sources, including Patricia Ward Biederman, Black Sun Books, Alfred Dasburg, Elizabeth W. DeHuff, Edward J. Foote, Anton V. Long, and Lawrence Clark Powell. The series is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, and Other Papers. There are two original letters from Luhan, one to Robert Edmund Jones, printed articles on Luhan by Biederman, Eya Fechin, and Powell, a couple photographs, including a poloroid image of a pencil drawing of Luhan by Maurice Sterne, and the well-known portrait of Luhan painted by Mary Foote.
Oversize material, housed in box 6, contains items from Series I, Series II, and Series VI. Restricted Fragile material is housed in box 7.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Psychoanalysis; Florence (Italy); Taos (N.M.); Photographic prints; Authors; Becker, Charlotte; Brett, Dorothy, 1883-1977; Brill, A. A. (Abraham Arden), 1874-1948; Foote, Mary Hallock, 1847-1938; Hausner, Eric P.; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Jeffers, Una, 1884 or 1885-1950; Johnson, Walter Willard, 1897-1968; Jones, Robert Edmond, 1887-1954; Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1879-1962; Reed, John, 1887-1920; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964
- Charlotte Becker Purchase, 1895-1940; Series I; 11
  Scope and Contents
  Purchased from Charlotte Becker on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1964
  Series I, Charlotte Becker Purchase, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, Photographs, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1908-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Johnson, Walter Willard ("Spud"), 1936 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - WRITINGS OF MABEL DODGE LUHAN
    - "The Dust Within the Rock," review, mimeograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Mabel Dodge..." article, printed version, 1922 Aug 17
    - "Mabel Dodge's Article on 'Pass'd!..." article, printed version, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Women Who Seek..." article, printed version (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Photographs of Mabel Dodge Luhan, [ca. 1895-1915] (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      With John Evans
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Clippings, 1923-32, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Printed business card, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Edmund R. Brill Gifts, 1917-1951; Series II; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Gifts of Edmund R. Brill, 1966-77
  Series II, Edmund R. Brill Gifts, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, Photographs, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Brill, A. A. (Abraham Arden), 1925-49 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
    - Brill, Edmund, 1938-51 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bull, Nina, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - New Mexico Historical Review, 1935 Apr (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Reed, John, [1917?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Tindall, William [York?], 1936 Sep (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Other correspondence, 1926-43, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Includes third party correspondence from Frieda Lawrence to "Dr. Brill" and Richard [Aldington] to D. H. Lawrence
  - WRITINGS OF MABEL DODGE LUHAN
    - "Hildegarde: Eight Years After," typescript carbon, corrected, [1948?] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Una and Robin" (Part One), typescript carbon, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Una and Robin in Taos" (Part II), typescript carbon, 1938 Dec (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Photographs of "Los Gallos" by Abraham Arden Brill, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Clipping, n.d.
    - Mabel Dodge Luhan watercolor, n.d. (Box ART, Folder 25)
    - Note in Mabel Dodge Luhan's hand (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Margaret Heyman Gift, n.d.; Series III; 7
  Gift of Margaret Heyman, 1985
  Series III, Margaret Heyman Gift, is arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Brett, Dorothy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Brill, Mrs. Abaham Arden and unidentified woman (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Heyman, Mrs. Marcus Babcock and Mrs. Abraham Arden Brill (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Jeffers, Robinson and family (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Luhan, Tony, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Groups of people, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Includes Dorothy Brett, Mrs. A. A. Brill, Mrs. M. B. Heyman, and Tony Luhan
- Walter Willard Johnson Purchase, 1927-1958; Series IV; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Purchased from Walter Willard Johnson on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1965
  Series III, Walter Willard Johnson Purchase, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings of Mabel Dodge Luhan, and Others Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Johnson, Walter Willard, 1927-58, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34-39)
    - Other correspondence, 1933-58, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - WRITINGS OF MABEL DODGE LUHAN
    - "Another Old Timer Gone," obituary, holograph, 1949 Aug 22 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "The Apparent and the Real," article, holograph, corrected (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Aspen," [article?], holograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Business as Usual," article, holograph, corrected, 1949 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Derision is Easy," narrative, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Edge of Taos Desert, holograph, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
    - "Family Affairs"
      - Holograph and typescript, corrected, 1933 Aug (Box 3, Folder 48-50)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (cancelled pages), 1933 Aug (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
    - "The Happy Hospital at Embudo," article, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Inevitable," poem, holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - ["It is very difficult..."], open letter [to Taos Valley News ], holograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Movers & Shakers
      - Holograph (Part I), corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Holograph (Part II), corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - Holograph and typescript (Part II), corrected (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - "Shopping Present and Past," article, holograph, corrected (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - ["Speaking of parking..."], open letter, holograph, 1949 Jun 14 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - "Taos-Unrevisited," article, holograph, corrected, 1949 Jun 5 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - "Water of Life," novel, holograph, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - "The Whole is Greater than the Part," article, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Winter in Taos, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64-65)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Bureau of Indian Affairs press release, 1952 Sep 16 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Drawing (fragment), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - "Informal Biographical Sketch of Mabel Dodge Luhan," drafts, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected by Luhan, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Notes in Mabel Dodge Luhan's hand (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Richard B. Streeper Gift, 1946-1958; Series V; 4
  Gift of Richard B. Streeper, 1979
  Series V, Richard B. Streeper Gift, is arranged chronologically by date.
  - Correspondence, 1946-58, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70-73)
- Carl Van Vechten Gifts, 1885-1952; Series VI; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Gifts of Carl Van Vechten, 1953-[60?]
  Series VI, Carl Van Vechten Gifts, is organized into two subseries: Writings and Photographs.
  - WRITINGS
    - "The Eye of the Beholder," printed version, The Masses, 1917 Oct (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - "Georgia O'Keeffe in Taos," article, printed version, Creative Art, 1931 Jun (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - "Portrait of the Villa Curonia," typescript, bound, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 76)
      Includes photographs by Jacques-Emile Blanche and copy of Gertrude Stein's "Portrait of Mabel Dodge at the Villa Curonia"
    - "The Santos of New Mexico," article, printed version, The Arts, 1925 Mar (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1885-1952 (Box 5, Folder 78)
      Includes Tony Luhan
    - Luhan, Tony, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Mabel Dodge Luhan's house (Los Gallos) in Taos, 1926, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 80)
      Includes photograph by Alan Sylls
    - Mabel Dodge Luhan's house (Villa Curonia) in Florence, n.d.
- Material from Other Sources, 1912-1984; Series VII; 10
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Sources indicated on individual folders.
  Series VII, Material from Other Sources, is organized into four subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Photographs, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Jones, Robert Edmond (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Wilson, "Mrs.", 1920 Apr 21 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - WRITINGS
    - Biederman, Patricia Ward
      - "A Footnote in the History of Her Time," printed version, Spree, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Fechin, Eya
      - "Teenage Memories of Taos," printed version, American West, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark
      - "Southwest Classics Reread: Lady of Taos," printed version, Westways, 1973 Jan (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1921 Aug (Box 5, Folder 86)
      With Tony Luhan, Mary Foote, and Alfred Dasburg
      Photograph by John Evans
    - Drawing of Mabel Dodge Luhan by Maurice Sterne, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Clippings, 1962-81 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - "Mabel Dodge Luhan was round and square" button (Box 5, Folder 88a)
    - Painting of Mabel Dodge Luhan by Mary Foote, [1912?] (Box ART, Folder 89)
    - Printed ephemera, 1960-80, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 90)
- Oversize, Date; 1.67; (1 box)
  - New York City Journal version of "Mabel Dodge..." (In Series I), 1917 Aug 22 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Clippings (In Series I), 1932, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Santa Fe New Mexican clipping (In Series II), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Photograph of "Los Gallos" (In Series VI) (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Photograph of "Villa Curonia" (In Series VI), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 95)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 2 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Box 1, folder 12 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Box 2, folder 34 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Box 2, folder 37 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Box 2, folder 38 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Box 2, folder 40 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Box 5, folder 72 (Box 7, Folder 102)